<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Read Ya!</title><link href="http://www.readya.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.readya.org/feeds/letters.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.readya.org/</id><updated>2014-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>The Magicians</title><link href="http://www.readya.org/2014/the-magicians/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Nathan</name></author><id>tag:www.readya.org,2014-05-25:2014/the-magicians/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello, friends,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sitting down to write the second installment of ReadYa, and it's
been over a year since the first arrived in your Inbox. You may not
even remember signing up to receive it. At the time I billed it as a
&amp;quot;bi-weekly newsletter on young adult literature, old and new.&amp;quot; Let's
just call it &amp;quot;periodic&amp;quot; rather than &amp;quot;bi-weekly&amp;quot;. So what is it that
prompted me to dust off the QWERTY and write to you again, after so
much time? Magicians. &lt;a class="reference internal" href="#id1"&gt;The Magicians&lt;/a&gt;, that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a while since a book made me feel the way XXX YYY's The
Magicians did. Liar and Spy did it. Jo Walton's Among Others. But it's
rarified company. The feeling that I'd rather sit and read &lt;em&gt;this book&lt;/em&gt;
than do almost anything else. I knew I had to write to you about The
Magicians just a few days after starting it. I arrived at the office
early, which is usually my favorite time to be at work: it's quiet and
still, and I can ease into my day without distraction. I sat down at
my desk, leaned back in my chair, and looked up and out the skylight,
and I felt incredibly sad that it would be hours before I picked up
The Magicians again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd heard The Magicians described as a blend of Narnia and Hogwarts
before picking it up, but that shorthand does a disservice to everyone
involved. Yes, there is a magical world called Fillory. And yes, there
is a school of magic, Brakebills. But the comparisons end there. The
Magicians takes place not in a world of noble deeds and divine
justice: it takes place in a world where people are mean to one
another, they're insecure and afraid, and they get bored. It takes
place in a world where you believe that the only way to survive is to
escape. It's a world that felt incredibly real and accurate to me, a
world that I can inhabit at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quentin, our protaganist, is smart. Very, very smart. And bored.
Brookyln is his home, but it feels like a cage. And any color pales in
comparison to Fillory, a world described in a series of young adult
books which Quentin thinks he &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have outgrown a long time ago.
I imagine that when Quentin is sitting in class, taking an exam in a
blue book, he looks out the window and imagines Fillory outside of it,
and his chest fills with grief that it is not really there, that
instead he is writing long hand in Number 2 pencil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Quentin is invited to matriculate at a school of magic, wonderous
things happen. And after a whlie he realizes that feeling doens't go
away, there's always something more to want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Magicians evoked a breadth of feelings in me as I read. I felt
excitement and suspense as Quentin navigates the halls of Brakebills
and learns magic. I felt sadness and empathy and he tries to figure
out what it is he wants, and continues to come up short. (How many
times have I known what I wanted, but felt unable to or unworthy of
articulating it?) And I felt sadness when things didn't turn out for
characters the ways I hoped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am almost afraid to read the sequel to The Magicians, The XXX Magic
Magic; I fell so completely in love with The Magicians that I'm not
sure what could follow it. But I think everyone should read The
Magicians, especially anyone who ever felt like their adolescence was
something to be sloughed off when their life &amp;quot;really&amp;quot; began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XOXO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class="target" id="id1"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Liar and Spy</title><link href="http://www.readya.org/2013/liar-and-spy/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-05-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Nathan</name></author><id>tag:www.readya.org,2013-05-14:2013/liar-and-spy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="" class="align-left" src="/static/images/liar-spy.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A secret club of two. Science class. &lt;em&gt;Gym&lt;/em&gt; class. The weird kid who's always drawing in class instead of paying attention. Bullies. These are all things that I remember from middle school, and they're all in &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17308183-liar-and-spy"&gt;Liar and Spy&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.goodreads.com/author/show/175329.Rebecca_Stead"&gt;Rebecca Stead&lt;/a&gt;. And in a way, they're all things that are still a part of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first heard about Rebecca Stead in 2010, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yergler.net/blog/2010/01/24/read-when-you-reach-me-and-first-light-by-rebecca-stead/"&gt;when I read&lt;/a&gt; &amp;quot;When You Reach Me&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;First Light&amp;quot;. There are days when doing anything but picking up a book seems like too much effort, and sometimes that feeling hits when I'm supposed to be working. In those moments I usually trawl the internet, searching for any author whose name comes to mind. It was in one of those fugues that I discovered that Stead had published &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; in October, and snapped back to reality and ordered it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; is the story of Georges (named for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georges_Seurat"&gt;Georges Surat&lt;/a&gt;; &amp;quot;the 's' is silent&amp;quot;, he informs the reader), and his new neighbor, Safer. Safer lives on the sixth floor of the building that Georges and his family have just moved to. Georges father lost his job as an architect, and they were forced to sell their house, leaving behind a place that was clearly significant for Georges. Safer is convinced that &amp;quot;Mr. X&amp;quot; on the fourth floor is up to no good, and that it's up to Georges and him to do something about it. That story is a great hook, but the real joy in &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; is everything that surrounds and supports that story-line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's something about the parents in &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot;; they're flawed, they're human. Was YA fiction always like this? I don't remember parents ever showing up as more than a foil growing up, but reading &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot;, I wanted to know more about their stories, too. Georges' Dad, tries to put on a brave face, but stands in front of the bookcase as they unpack, trying to figure out if the blue or red book goes up next; is there something more there? (I think so; &amp;quot;Once, Mom came home from work and discovered that he had turned all the books around so that the bindings were against the wall and the pages faced out. He said it was calming not to have all those words floating around and &amp;quot;creating static&amp;quot;. Mom made him turn them back.&amp;quot;) His dad &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; Georges. He's trying to build a new business after being laid off, trying to be Georges' buddy, but there's an almost palpable weight on his shoulders. When he asks Georges to &amp;quot;tell him stuff&amp;quot; (about his day, his life), it feels like he's really asking, &amp;quot;tell me something so I can forget.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safer's Mom is a photographer. Stead never comes out and says it, but it seems obvious that Safer's family is better off, or at least more certain about their place in the world. Safer has two sibling, Candy and Pigeon, and the description of their apartment evoked this feeling of space and light. Georges thinks his mom would describe Safer's family as &amp;quot;smart bohemians&amp;quot;: they waited to name their children until they thought they understood something about their personalities. (Candy, Safer's younger sister, does indeed love candy.) It's obvious they care about their kids, but they also &lt;em&gt;respect&lt;/em&gt; them, and expect them to be able to make up their own mind about things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there are the bullies, led by Dallas and Carter. The kids who call Georges &amp;quot;Gorgeous&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Jor-Jess&amp;quot;. I admit that I cringed every time Georges tried to ignore their taunts, remembering my grandpa's advice, &amp;quot;they wouldn't tease you if they didn't like you.&amp;quot; (Twenty-five years later, and I'm still not convinced.) The bullies aren't the center of &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot;, but Stead manages to use them to round out the middle school experience without feeling like a cliche. And the resolution of that story line manages to empower without feeling saccharine or unrealistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="/static/images/640px-A_Sunday_on_La_Grande_Jatte%2C_Georges_Seurat%2C_1884.png" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&amp;quot;A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte&amp;quot;, Georges Seurat, 1884&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally there's &amp;quot;Sir Ott&amp;quot;, the silent &amp;quot;character&amp;quot; in &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot;, and in a way the thematic backdrop. Sir Ott is the name Georges and his parents give to the reproduction of a Seurat pointillism, which hangs in the living room. When they move into the apartment, it's the first thing they put away (hang), and it signifies where &amp;quot;home&amp;quot; is. Stead never tells us specifically which work Sir Ott is, but I pictured it at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Sunday_Afternoon_on_the_Island_of_La_Grande_Jatte"&gt;A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte&lt;/a&gt; (and the few details, like buying the print at The Art Institute of Chicago, match up). Georges' mom encourages him to see Sir Ott as a metaphor for life: what's going on right now may be unpleasant, but if we pull back it's just one little dot in a beautiful painting. Georges takes this metaphor as his mantra, reminding himself of it when he's picked on and bullied. But when Georges finally tells his dad what's going on, his dad reminds him: &amp;quot;The dots matter.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should read &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; regardless of whether you have bullies, weird neighbors, or secret clubs in your life. It more than repays the small investment of time, and helps remind you that &lt;em&gt;the dots matter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-right" src="/static/images/mixed-up-files.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was saddened to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/23/books/e-l-konigsburg-author-is-dead-at-83.html?_r=0"&gt;read of the death&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._L._Konigsburg"&gt;E. L. Konigsburg&lt;/a&gt;. I have a beat up copy of &amp;quot;From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler&amp;quot; on my shelf, and still love the cover text: &amp;quot;Claudia knew she had to run away; the question was -- where should she run to?&amp;quot; My copy is old enough to be missing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cataloging_in_Publication"&gt;cataloging-in-publication&lt;/a&gt; and ISBN information, so dating it exactly is difficult, but it's one of two books I've been carrying around since (at least) fourth grade (the other is &amp;quot;Harriet the Spy&amp;quot;). I've started gently re-reading it, and am reminded of hiding in the school library during recess to read when I was a kid. Reading the obituary, I realized there's a whole collection of her work that I haven't read yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with Konigsburg's Wikipedia entry, I found out a little more about her biography. She went to college to study chemistry, because the point of college was to become a &amp;quot;something&amp;quot;, and was the first person in her family to receive a degree. It wasn't until she had two children that she started taking painting lessons at an adult education center, and started writing when her third child started school. I think that makes the fact that she self-illustrated &lt;em&gt;Frankweiler&lt;/em&gt; more fascinating: she started expressing herself one way, shifted, and then incorporated what she'd learned before to make the whole more compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.scholastic.com/teachers/article/el-konigsburg-interview-transcript"&gt;transcript of an interview&lt;/a&gt; with Scholastic is a fascinating read: &amp;quot;I think it's important to experience kindness, so that you can experience it more in the future. ... I think that if you have not observed kindness, you will not recognize it. You have to experience kindness in order to be kind. And you have to lay down those emotional pathways.&amp;quot; (You'd think a website with a name so etymologically close to &lt;em&gt;scholar&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;scholarship&lt;/em&gt; would understand the value of dating their resources. Alas.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading this far; I hope you're interested in &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; now, and I hope you'll read it and love it as much as I did. If you decide to read it, let me know what you think. Until next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XOXO.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>