<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Read Ya!</title><link>http://www.readya.org/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><item><title>Liar and Spy</title><link>http://www.readya.org/2013/liar-and-spy/</link><description>&lt;img alt="" class="align-left" src="/images/liar-spy.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A secret club of two. Science class. &lt;em&gt;Gym&lt;/em&gt; class. The weird kid who's always drawing in class instead of paying attention. Bullies. These are all things that I remember from middle school, and they're all in &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17308183-liar-and-spy"&gt;Liar and Spy&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.goodreads.com/author/show/175329.Rebecca_Stead"&gt;Rebecca Stead&lt;/a&gt;. And in a way, they're all things that are still a part of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first heard about Rebecca Stead in 2010, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yergler.net/blog/2010/01/24/read-when-you-reach-me-and-first-light-by-rebecca-stead/"&gt;when I read&lt;/a&gt; &amp;quot;When You Reach Me&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;First Light&amp;quot;. There are days when doing anything but picking up a book seems like too much effort, and sometimes that feeling hits when I'm supposed to be working. In those moments I usually trawl the internet, searching for any author whose name comes to mind. It was in one of those fugues that I discovered that Stead had published &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; in October, and snapped back to reality and ordered it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; is the story of Georges (named for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georges_Seurat"&gt;Georges Surat&lt;/a&gt;; &amp;quot;the 's' is silent&amp;quot;, he informs the reader), and his new neighbor, Safer. Safer lives on the sixth floor of the building that Georges and his family have just moved to. Georges father lost his job as an architect, and they were forced to sell their house, leaving behind a place that was clearly significant for Georges. Safer is convinced that &amp;quot;Mr. X&amp;quot; on the fourth floor is up to no good, and that it's up to Georges and him to do something about it. That story is a great hook, but the real joy in &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; is everything that surrounds and supports that story-line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's something about the parents in &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot;; they're flawed, they're human. Was YA fiction always like this? I don't remember parents ever showing up as more than a foil growing up, but reading &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot;, I wanted to know more about their stories, too. Georges' Dad, tries to put on a brave face, but stands in front of the bookcase as they unpack, trying to figure out if the blue or red book goes up next; is there something more there? (I think so; &amp;quot;Once, Mom came home from work and discovered that he had turned all the books around so that the bindings were against the wall and the pages faced out. He said it was calming not to have all those words floating around and &amp;quot;creating static&amp;quot;. Mom made him turn them back.&amp;quot;) His dad &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; Georges. He's trying to build a new business after being laid off, trying to be Georges' buddy, but there's an almost palpable weight on his shoulders. When he asks Georges to &amp;quot;tell him stuff&amp;quot; (about his day, his life), it feels like he's really asking, &amp;quot;tell me something so I can forget.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safer's Mom is a photographer. Stead never comes out and says it, but it seems obvious that Safer's family is better off, or at least more certain about their place in the world. Safer has two sibling, Candy and Pigeon, and the description of their apartment evoked this feeling of space and light. Georges thinks his mom would describe Safer's family as &amp;quot;smart bohemians&amp;quot;: they waited to name their children until they thought they understood something about their personalities. (Candy, Safer's younger sister, does indeed love candy.) It's obvious they care about their kids, but they also &lt;em&gt;respect&lt;/em&gt; them, and expect them to be able to make up their own mind about things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there are the bullies, led by Dallas and Carter. The kids who call Georges &amp;quot;Gorgeous&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Jor-Jess&amp;quot;. I admit that I cringed every time Georges tried to ignore their taunts, remembering my grandpa's advice, &amp;quot;they wouldn't tease you if they didn't like you.&amp;quot; (Twenty-five years later, and I'm still not convinced.) The bullies aren't the center of &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot;, but Stead manages to use them to round out the middle school experience without feeling like a cliche. And the resolution of that story line manages to empower without feeling saccharine or unrealistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="/images/640px-A_Sunday_on_La_Grande_Jatte%2C_Georges_Seurat%2C_1884.png" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&amp;quot;A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte&amp;quot;, Georges Seurat, 1884&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally there's &amp;quot;Sir Ott&amp;quot;, the silent &amp;quot;character&amp;quot; in &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot;, and in a way the thematic backdrop. Sir Ott is the name Georges and his parents give to the reproduction of a Seurat pointillism, which hangs in the living room. When they move into the apartment, it's the first thing they put away (hang), and it signifies where &amp;quot;home&amp;quot; is. Stead never tells us specifically which work Sir Ott is, but I pictured it at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Sunday_Afternoon_on_the_Island_of_La_Grande_Jatte"&gt;A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte&lt;/a&gt; (and the few details, like buying the print at The Art Institute of Chicago, match up). Georges' mom encourages him to see Sir Ott as a metaphor for life: what's going on right now may be unpleasant, but if we pull back it's just one little dot in a beautiful painting. Georges takes this metaphor as his mantra, reminding himself of it when he's picked on and bullied. But when Georges finally tells his dad what's going on, his dad reminds him: &amp;quot;The dots matter.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should read &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; regardless of whether you have bullies, weird neighbors, or secret clubs in your life. It more than repays the small investment of time, and helps remind you that &lt;em&gt;the dots matter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-right" src="/images/mixed-up-files.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was saddened to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/04/23/books/e-l-konigsburg-author-is-dead-at-83.html?_r=0"&gt;read of the death&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._L._Konigsburg"&gt;E. L. Konigsburg&lt;/a&gt;. I have a beat up copy of &amp;quot;From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler&amp;quot; on my shelf, and still love the cover text: &amp;quot;Claudia knew she had to run away; the question was -- where should she run to?&amp;quot; My copy is old enough to be missing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cataloging_in_Publication"&gt;cataloging-in-publication&lt;/a&gt; and ISBN information, so dating it exactly is difficult, but it's one of two books I've been carrying around since (at least) fourth grade (the other is &amp;quot;Harriet the Spy&amp;quot;). I've started gently re-reading it, and am reminded of hiding in the school library during recess to read when I was a kid. Reading the obituary, I realized there's a whole collection of her work that I haven't read yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with Konigsburg's Wikipedia entry, I found out a little more about her biography. She went to college to study chemistry, because the point of college was to become a &amp;quot;something&amp;quot;, and was the first person in her family to receive a degree. It wasn't until she had two children that she started taking painting lessons at an adult education center, and started writing when her third child started school. I think that makes the fact that she self-illustrated &lt;em&gt;Frankweiler&lt;/em&gt; more fascinating: she started expressing herself one way, shifted, and then incorporated what she'd learned before to make the whole more compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.scholastic.com/teachers/article/el-konigsburg-interview-transcript"&gt;transcript of an interview&lt;/a&gt; with Scholastic is a fascinating read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;I think it's important to experience kindness, so that you can experience it more in the future. ... I think that if you have not observed kindness, you will not recognize it. You have to experience kindness in order to be kind. And you have to lay down those emotional pathways.&amp;quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(You'd think a website with a name so etymologically close to &lt;em&gt;scholar&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;scholarship&lt;/em&gt; would understand the value of dating their resources. Alas.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading this far; I hope you're interested in &amp;quot;Liar and Spy&amp;quot; now, and I hope you'll read it and love it as much as I did. If you decide to read it, let me know what you think. Until next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XOXO.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Nathan</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.readya.org,2013-05-14:2013/liar-and-spy/</guid></item></channel></rss>